Finding Aid for Bright Sheng Papers, 1962-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bright Sheng papers 1962-2004, 1982-2004
Sheng, Bright.
13 oversize boxes 22 boxes total
11.5 linear feet
0497 Aa 2
Bright Sheng, a composer born in China, is also renown as a conductor, pianist, and researcher. The Bright Sheng Collection contains the papers of University of Michigan composition professor Bright Sheng. In addition to Sheng's own files and correspondence, it includes manuscript, printed, and published versions of his scores (printed scores are for musicians' use, while published scores are for a wider audience), published and unpublished recordings of his works, interviews, programs and reviews featuring his works, and work from Sheng's students. Also included are field recordings and an audio diary from the 2000 Silk Road project in China.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was initially received from Bright Sheng in 2004. Periodic accessions are anticipated. Donor No. 9540.
The papers are open with the exception of certain student compositions and recordings that fall under provisions of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act.
Bright Sheng (1955- ) is the Leonard Bernstein Distinguished University Professor of Music in the Composition Department of the University of Michigan's School of Music. Now a widely-renowned composer, conductor, pianist, and researcher, Sheng embarked in music as a career as a teenager in China in the remote province of Qinghai, where he was sent during the Cultural Revolution. After several years performing and studying folk music and dances, Sheng was one of the first students to be admitted to the Shanghai Conservatory of Music when China's universities reopened in 1978. In 1982, Sheng moved to New York, obtaining graduate degrees at Queens College (M.A.) and Columbia University (D.M.A.). While a student, Sheng not only won praise from teachers Leonard Bernstein, George Perle, and others, but also gained citations and awards from the National Endowment for the Arts, the Kennedy Center, and several foundations.
Since 1998, Sheng has been the Artistic Advisor to the highly regarded Silk Road Project, an international program that identifies, archives, and interprets musical traditions of the peoples in the regions of the trade routes that once were the primary linkage between Europe and the Far East. In this capacity he has conducted field research in outlying provinces in China and has both published articles and composed musical works based on his experiences and findings. Other highlights of Sheng's career include several world premieres by artists and ensembles such as the Boston Symphony Orchestra, the New York Philharmonic, Yo-Yo Ma, and Emanuel Ax; collaborations with librettists Andrew Porter, Colin Graham, David Henry Hwang, and others; and numerous guest lectureships, artistic directorships, and residencies at universities and conservatories nationwide. Additionally, in 1999 Sheng was commissioned by the White House to create a new work for a state dinner honoring Chinese Premiere Zhou Rongji. In 2001, Sheng was granted the prestigious MacArthur Foundation Fellowship.
Orchestras and ensembles have recorded Sheng's music on a variety of labels. Sheng's music is published exclusively by G. Schirmer Inc., and he is represented as a conductor and pianist by Columbia Artists Management.
For a fuller biography, see Pamela Chen's essay in Appendix 1. Pamela Chen is a doctoral student in Composition at Michigan State University.
The Bright Sheng Collection contains the papers of University of Michigan composition professor Bright Sheng. It is comprised of 17 series: Biographical, 1982-c2000; Correspondence, 1962-2004; Professional, 1997-1998; Career, 1988-1995; Program Notes [undated]; Awards and Citations, 1984-2003; Photographs, 1985-2004; Reviews, 1986-2004; Programs, 1973-2003; Libretti, 1999-2003; Published Scores, 1988-1999; Printed Scores, 1982-2002; Manuscripts and Revised Scores, 1985-2004; Audio Recordings [undated]; Student Works, 1996-2004; Silk Road Trip, 2000; and Moving Images, 1985-2003. Together, these series document Sheng's career from his early days as a student to his current status as world-renowned composer and professor.
The first six series in the Bright Sheng Collection are extremely short, with a combined physical extent of approximately .5 linear foot. The Biographical, 1982-c2000 series is comprised of a single folder containing biographical material about Sheng. The Correspondence, 1962-2004 series contains topical files of Sheng's correspondence with colleagues in China, with his professors, and with his family, as well as a partial chronological file of correspondence falling outside of those three categories. The Professional, 1997-1998 series includes an article written by Sheng, as well as articles in Chinese about Sheng's music. The Career, 1988-1995 series contains materials related to Sheng's various appointments and positions over the years. The Program Notes series contains an article about the Sung Dynasty and the work Two Poems from the Sung Dynasty. The Awards and Citations, 1984-2003 series includes materials related to various honors Sheng has received in the course of his career, including a MacArthur 'Genius' grant and the University of Michigan's Leonard Bernstein Distinguished University Professorship.
Subjects:
Sheng, Bright, 1955-; Composition (Music); Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Music--Instruction and study.; Music--Manuscripts.; Composers--United States.; Pi pa with orchestra.; Orchestral music.; Music--China--History and criticism.; Silk Road--Songs and music.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; Scores.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Sheng, Bright.; Bernstein, Leonard.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Sheng, Bright.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; Orchestral music.; Composition (Music); Folk music--China.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Biographical 1982-2000
  - Biographical Materials, 1982-ca. 2000, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1962-2004
  - Topical Files
    - Correspondence with colleagues in China 1962-1988 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with Professors 1982-1993 (Box 1)
      (George Perle, Leonard Bernstein)
    - Correspondence with Family 1992 (Box 1)
  - Chronological Files
    - Chicago period 1989 Fall-1992 Spring (Box 1)
    - Seattle period 1992 Fall-1995 Spring (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor period 1995 Fall-2004 (Box 1)
- Professional 1997-1998
  - Article written by Bright Sheng (published) 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Papers about Bright Sheng's Music in Chinese 1998 (Box 1)
- Career 1988-1995
  - Career Materials 1988-1995 (Box 1)
- Program Notes
  - Program Notes 1986, undated (Box 1)
- Awards and Citations 1984-2003
  - Awards and Citations 1984-1995 (Box 1)
  - White House Commission and State Dinner 1999 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Citations (including MacArthur Fellowship) 2001-2003 (Box 1)
  - Distinguished University Professorship 2003
- Photographs 1985-2004
  Finally, the Photographs, 1985-2004 series contains negatives of Sheng, his family, colleagues, and associates in both informal settings and at various premiers, performances, and other engagements. These copy negatives were made from prints loaned by Sheng. Notable figures in these photographs include Yo-Yo Ma, Peter Serkin, Leonard Bernstein, Kurt Mazur, Emanuel Ax, Aaron Copland, and David Henry Hwang. In the detailed listing describing the photographs in the boxlist, numbers in square brackets are arbitrarily assigned identifying numbers, while the number in parentheses is the Bentley Library's negative number.
  - Bright Sheng with Hugh Wolff (conductor), [1] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18700)
  - From left to right: Mendy Wager (friend), Christoph Eschenbach (conductor), Bright Sheng, and Judith Pisar (friend) 2004, [2] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18701)
  - Bright Sheng and Gerard Schwarz (conductor), [3] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18702)
  - From left to right: Bright Sheng, George and Arlene Cheng (patrons), Yo-Yo Ma (cellist), after the premiere of Sheng's Seven Tunes Heard in China for solo cello at Irvine Barclay Theatre. October 9th 1995, [4] (Box 1)
    (The piece was commissioned by Dr. George Cheng as a tribute to his wife Arlene Cheng)
    (neg. na18703)
  - Sheng with Houston Grand Opera after the performance of his opera The Song of Majnun, ca. 1994-1995 (neg. na18704), [5] (Box 1)
  - Bright Sheng with Peter Serkin (pianist) (neg. na18705), [6] (Box 1)
  - Bright Sheng with Samuel Wong (conductor) (neg. na18706), [7] (Box 1)
  - Bright Sheng with the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center after the Premiere of Sheng's Concertino for Clarinet and String Quartet at Lincoln Center, 1994, [8] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18707)
  - Bright Sheng conducting the San Francisco Symphony, when he was Artistic Director of the Symphony's "Wet Ink 93" Music Festival 1993, [9] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18708)
  - Left to Right: Lan Shui (conductor), Cho-Liang Lin (Violinist), and Bright Sheng after the performance of Sheng's China Dreams with Singapore Symphony Orchestra, ca. 1997-2000, [10] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18709)
  - Bright Sheng with Mary Sue Coleman (the president of University of Michigan) after he gave his lecture for the Leonard Bernstein distinguished University Professorship February, 2004, [11] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18710)
  - Bright Sheng with Leonard Bernstein and the performers after the Premiere of Arias and Barcarolles (music composed by Leonard Bernstein, orchestration by Bright Sheng), ca. 1988, [12] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18711)
  - Left to right: Margret Fieldman (Sheng's sister), Bright Sheng, Kurt Mazur (conductor), Alice and David Cheng (Sheng's parents), after the premiere of H'un at NYC with the New York Philharmonic, 1993, [13] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18712)
  - Left to Right: Yo-Yo Ma (cellist), Bright Sheng, and Wu Man (pipa player) at the premiere of Sheng's Three Songs for Pipa and Cello during the State Dinner hosted by President Clinton, honoring Chinese Premier Zhou Rongji at the White House, April 1999, [14] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18713)
  - Left to Right: Bright Sheng, Tom Robertetlo (flutist), and David Effron (conductor) at Brevard Music Center where Sheng was in composer-residency during Brevard Music festival July, 2004, [15] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18714)
  - Bright Sheng and David Zinman (conductor) (neg. na18715), [16] (Box 1)
  - Bright Sheng and Leonard Slatkin after the premiere of William Bolcom's work The Innocent Songs at Hill Auditorium, February 2004, [17] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18716)
  - Left to Right: Robert Spano (conductor), Bright Sheng, and Emanuel Ax (pianist) at the premiere of Sheng's Red Silk Dance with the Boston Symphony, January, 2000, [18] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18717)
  - Left to Right: Leonard Bernstein, Aaron Copland and Bright Sheng at Tanglewood Music Center when Sheng was a student of Composers Workshop at the Music Center 1985, [19] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18718)
  - Leonard Bernstein conducting, [20] (Box 1)
    (A gift to Bright Sheng from Leonard Bernstein in 1990)
    (neg. na18719)
  - Sheng with Silk Road Project Tanglewood Workshop at Tanglewood Music Center 2000, [21] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18720)
  - [Does not exist], [22] (Box 1)
  - Bright Sheng and Yo-Yo Ma after the premiere of Seven Tunes Heard in China for Solo Violoncello in Orange County, California, 1995, [23] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18721)
  - Bright Sheng with Valery Gergiev (conductor) after Gergiev conducted Strauss' Salome with the Metropolitan Opera in New York City, April 2004, [24] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18725)
  - Bright Sheng with Leonard Bernstein at Fountainbleau 1989, [25] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18726)
  - Bright Sheng with Neemi Jarvi (conductor), [26] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18727)
  - Bright Sheng with David Henry Hwang (the librettist of Sheng's opera The Silver River, [27] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18728)
  - Bright Sheng with Arthur Feigen (conductor), [28] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18729)
  - Bright Sheng with Takacs Quartet after the premiere of Bright Sheng's String Quartet No. 3, 1993, [29] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18730)
  - Cho-Liang Lin (violinist), Bright Sheng and Hui-Chang Yan (conductor) with the Hong Kong Chinese Orchestra after the performance of Sheng's Spring Dreams, 1993 (neg. na18731), [30] (Box 1)
  - Left to Right: The team of the premiere of Bright Sheng's The Song of Majnun: Andrew Porter (librettist), Bright Sheng, Colin Graham (director), and Richard Buchley (conductor) at Chicago, 1992, [31] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18732)
  - Bright Sheng with musicians of the Seattle Symphony after Bright Sheng conducted Stravinsky's The Soldier's Tale, [32] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18733)
  - Bright Sheng with Heiichiro Oyama (violist), the director of Santa Fe Chamber Music Festival 1993, [33] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18734)
  - Bright Sheng with Maximiano Valdes (conductor) after a performance of H'un by the Buffalo Philharmonic Orchestra, 1994, [34] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18735)
  - Bright Sheng with Yahja Ling after a performance of H'un by the Cleveland Orchestra, ca. 1990-1993, [35] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18736)
  - Left to Right: Hugo Weigall, Bright Sheng, and Brena and Lee Freeman (patrons) at the premiere of The Song of Majnun, 1992, [36] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18737)
  - Bright Sheng and Thomas Dausgaord (the principal guest of the Danish National Symphony Orchestra) after a performance of H'un, ca. 1995, [37] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18738)
  - Bright Sheng and William Mclaughlin (conductor) after a performance of H'un by the Kansas City Symphony, 1994, [38] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18739)
  - Left to Right: Dennis and Susan Carlyle (patrons), Sheng, David Gockley (General Director of the Houston Grand Opera), [39] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18740)
  - Bright Sheng with Ward Holmquist, the conductor of the Houston Grand Opera who recorded Sheng's The Song of Majnun in 1994, [40] (Box 1)
    (neg. na18741)
  - Left to Right: Ardis Krainik (the director of Chicago Lyrical Opera), Bright Sheng, Andrew Porter (the librettist of The Song of Majnun), Brena and Lee Freeman (patrons), 1992 (neg. na18742), [41]
- Reviews 1986-2004
  The Reviews, 1986-2004 series includes topically arranged press clippings regarding Sheng's compositions, performances, directorships, and recordings.
  - Publicity /Previews 1989-2004, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Composition Reviews
    - "H'un" (Lacerations) -- in memoriam 1966-1976, Europe Tour, 1993 (Box 1)
    - "H'un" (Lacerations) -- in memoriam 1966-1976, 1988-2004 (Box 1)
    - Opera and Music Theater Works 1992-2003 (Box 1)
    - Orchestra and Chorus Works 1986-2004 (Box 1)
    - Chamber/Vocal/Solo Works 1987-2004 (Box 1)
  - Performance Reviews 1987-2003 (Box 1)
  - Directorship Reviews 1993-2002 (Box 1)
  - Recording Reviews 1992-2003
- Programs 1973-2003
  The chronologically-arranged Programs, 1973-2003 series contains both season schedules and individual performance stagebills dating from Sheng's days in China to the present. The programs feature both Sheng's own appearances and performances of his compositions, as well as seasons or performances for which Sheng acted as conductor or artistic director. Additionally, the series includes a few stagebills (for events not relating to Sheng or his music) that feature articles about Sheng.
  - 1973, 1980-1983, 1986, 1988-1993, undated, 20 folders (Box 2)
  - 1994-1998, 20 folders (Box 3)
  - 1999-2003, 11 folders (Box 4)
- Libretti 1999-2003
  The Libretti, 1999-2003 series contains libretti, souvenir programs, and outlines for two of Sheng's operatic works Silver River and Madam Mao.
  - The Silver River, (Libretto and Outline), 1997 Revised 1999 (Box 4)
  - Madam Mao, (Libretto and Program books), 2003 (Box 4)
- Published Scores 1988-1999
  The Published Scores, 1988-1999 and the Printed Scores, 1982-2002 series both include scores for many of Sheng's compositions arranged by genre of music (Chamber/Vocal/Solo, Choral/Orchestral, or Opera/Music Theater). The former contains G. Schirmer's printed scores for musicians' use, while the latter contains scores published for a wider audience.
  - Chamber/Vocal/Solo Works
    - Three Chinese Love Songs (score and parts), 1988 (Box 4)
    - Two Folk Songs from Qin Hai (score and parts), 1989 (Box 4)
    - My Song for Solo Piano, 1989 (Box 4)
    - The Stream Flows for Solo Violin, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Four Movements for Piano Trio (score and parts), 1990 (Box 4)
    - String Quartet No. 3 (score and parts), 1993 (Box 4)
    - Concertino for Clarinet and String Quartet 1994 (Box 4)
      (score and parts)
    - Seven Tunes Heard in China (Box 4)
  - Orchestra Works
    - H'un (Lacerations) -- in Memoriam 1966-1976, 1988 (Box 4)
    - China Dreams, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Flute Moon, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Opera/Music Theater
    - The Song of Majnun, 1992
- Printed Scores 1982-2002
  - Chamber/Vocal/Solo
    - Three Etudes for Solo Flute, 1982 Revised 1988 (Box 5)
    - Three Chinese Poems for Mezzo-Soprano and Piano, 1982-1992 (Box 5)
    - Seven Yadhtrib Variations for Solo Bassoo n, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Three Songs for Violoncello and Pipa, 1999 (Box 5)
    - String Quartet No. 4, 2000 (Box 5)
    - Tibetan Dance, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Distant Birthday Bells for Solo Piano, 2001 (Box 5)
  - Orchestra/Chorus
    - Two Poems from the Sung Dynasty, (soprano and orchestra -- single winds), 1995 (Box 5)
    - Two Folksongs from Qin Hai, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Fanfares for Orchestra, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Prelude for Orchestra, 1994 (Box 5)
      (triple winds)
    - Postcards, 1997 (Box 5)
      (chamber orchestra, double winds)
    - Spring Dreams, 1997 (Box 5)
      (violoncello and orchestra of traditional Chinese instruments)
    - Spring Dreams, 1998 (Box 5)
      (violin and orchestra of traditional Chinese instruments)
    - Tibetan Swing, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Two Poems for Violoncello and Orchestra, 1998 (Box 5)
      (violoncello and orchestra, triple winds)
    - Red Silk Dance, 1999 (Box 5)
      (piano and orchestra)
    - Nanking! Nanking!, 2000 (Box 5)
      (pipa and Orchestra)
  - Opera/Music Theater
    - The Song of Majnun Libretto (English) by Andrew Porter, 1992 (Box 5)
      (cast 8; chorus 16; orchestra 35)
    - May I Feel-an Opera in Seven Minutes, Words (English) by E. E. Cummings, 1996 (Box 5)
      (soprano, tenor and piano four hands)
    - The Silver River Libretto (English) by David Henry Hwang, 1997
      (cast 13; SATB chorus, orchestra: 2222/4331/h[3], strings)
- Manuscripts and Revised Scores 1985-2004
  The Manuscripts and Revised Scores, 1985-2004 series contains Sheng's original, hand-written scores, photocopies thereof, and printed scores with Sheng's hand-written revisions. The series highlights the revision and adaptation that are essential parts of Sheng's composition process by including multiple versions of some of his works. Also of note in the series are three manuscript versions of Leonard Bernstein's Arias and Barcarolles, as orchestrated by Bright Sheng. These manuscripts include Bernstein's notes as well as Sheng's. For document-housing purposes, size is used to distinguish the oversize versions from the regular size versions. Thus, researchers should look for versions in both size categories.
  - Regular sized Manuscripts and Revised Scores
    - Chamber/Vocal/Solo
      - The Stream Flows for Solo Violin, 1990 (Box 5)
      - Seven Tunes Heard in China, 1999 (Box 5)
        (revised according to CD)
      - String Quartet No. 4 (Silent Temple), 2000 (Box 5)
      - Boatmen's Song, 2004 (Box 5)
      - Mountain Echo and A Happy Sunny Day undated (Box 5)
        (chorus and piano)
    - Orchestra/Chorus
      - Red Silk Dance, November 1999 (Box 5)
      - Red Silk Dance, August 2001 (Box 5)
      - Red Silk Dance, circa 1999-2002 (Box 5)
  - Oversized Revised Scores
    - Chamber/Vocal/Solo Music
      - String Quartet Number 3 1993 (Box 6)
        (Old Version with revisions)
    - Orchestra/Chorus
      - Fanfare: Arrows to the Page, revised May 1996 (Box 6)
      - Fanfare I: Arrows to the Page, revised 1992-1997 (Box 6)
      - Prelude for Orchestra, revised November 1994 (Box 6)
      - Prelude for Orchestra, revised January 1995 (Box 6)
      - Symphonic Suite (China Dreams), revised September 1995 (Box 7)
        (The first movement only)
      - China Dreams, revised 1995 (Box 7)
      - Spring Dreams for Violoncello and Chinese Traditional Orchestra, revised circa 1997-1998 (Box 7)
      - Postcards, revised June 1998 (Box 7)
      - Nanking! Nanking!, revised February 2002 (Box 7)
      - The Song and Dance of Tears, revised December 2003 (Box 8)
      - The Song and Dance of Tears, revised April 2003 (Box 8)
      - Tibetan Swing, revised February 2003 (Box 8)
      - Red Silk Dance, revised 2001 (Box 8)
  - Oversized Manuscripts
    - Opera and Theater Music
      - The Song of Majnun, 1992 (Box 9)
        (the second version, arias)
      - Arias and Barcarolles composed by Leonard Bernstein, orchestration by Bright Sheng, undated, 3 folders (Box 9)
        (the first, second, and third versions, with Leonard Bernstein's handwriting)
    - Chamber/Vocal/Solo Music
      - Three Etudes for Solo Flute, 1992-1998 (Box 10)
        (the second version)
      - Three Chinese Love Songs, 1988 (Box 10)
        (the second version, score and parts)
      - The Stream Flows for Solo Viola, 1988 (Box 10)
    - Chamber/Vocal/Solo Music
      - My Song for Solo Piano, 1989 (Box 10)
      - Four Movements for Piano Trio, 1990 (Box 10)
      - The Stream Flows for Solo Violin, 1990 (Box 10)
      - Three Chinese Poems for Mezzo-Soprano and Piano, 1982-1992, 2 folders (Box 10)
        (the first and the second versions)
      - String Quartet No. 3, 1993 (Box 10)
      - Seven Short Yadhtrib Variations for Solo Bassoon, 1994 (Box 10)
        (the copy of the second version)
      - Seven Tunes Heard in China 1995 (Box 10)
      - A Tune from Childhood for Solo Clarinet, 1996 (Box 10)
      - A Happy Sunny Day, undated (Box 10)
        (the first version)
      - Three Songs for Pipa and Violoncello, 1999 (Box 11)
      - String Quartet No. 4, 2000, 2 folders (Box 11)
        (the first and second versions)
      - Tibetan Dance, 2001, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Distant Birthday Bells for Solo Piano, 2001 (Box 11)
        (the copy of the first version)
      - Three Tunes for Pipa and Erhu, 2003 (Box 11)
      - Fugato Variation for Solo Piano, 2003 (Box 11)
      - Boatmen's Song 2003, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Three Poems from Sung Dynasty for Soprano and Chamber Ensemble, 1985 (Box 12)
      - H'un (Lacerations) in Memoriam 1966-1976, 1988 (Box 12)
      - Two Folk Songs from Qin Hai, 1989 (Box 12)
        (score and parts, the second version)
      - China Dreams, 1995, 2 folders (Box 13)
        (the third movement only, the first and second versions)
      - Spring Dreams for Violoncello and Orchestra, 1997 (Box 13)
      - Flute Moon, 1999, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Red Silk Dance, 1999, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Nanking! Nanking!, 2000, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Tibetan Swing, 2002 (Box 14)
      - The Song and Dance of Tears, 2003, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - The Phoenix for Soprano and Orchestra, 2004, 2 folders
- Audio recordings